What did the Battle of Cannae actually
look like?
Modeling the Battle of Cannae in true
size is a gargantuan undertaking.
A battle featuring one of the largest
Roman armies ever assembled, whose
frontage was so vast that it would take
over 40 minutes to walk across, and so
deep that you could fit an entire soccer
field between the front and the rear
ranks.
Even Napoleonic artillery stationed at
one end of the [music] field would lack
the range to reach more than half of the
army before it.
Such are the scales we are dealing with.
Without the benefit of a time machine,
this has long been left a mystery.
However, in this series, we leverage the
expertise of historians [music] such as
Dr. Adrian Goldsworthy and the power of
tools like Unreal Engine 5 to bring the
past to life with the most detailed
simulation of this climactic battle ever
attempted.
From the often overlooked scale of the
city-sized camps which hosted the vast
armies assembled that day
to the hours-long logistical nightmare
of deploying 130,000
men from these camps into formations on
the field of battle.
And the stunning blow-by-blow phases by
which Hannibal managed the incredible
feat of enveloping and destroying
[music]
an army twice his size.
We bring you back in time to experience
it all from both a bird's-eye
perspective in the skies above
and the boots on the ground in the thick
of the action.
The skirmishers,
the cavalry,
the infantry,
and the generals.
The end result is a revolutionary new
way to not only visualize the massive
battles of antiquity, but to derive
[music] novel academic conclusions which
challenge how we understand them.
So, today let's dive in to this [music]
fascinating simulation.
This is the true size of the Battle of
Cannae.
>> Hey everyone, it's Julian. Uh no sponsor
segment here. I just wanted a chance to
speak to you human to human for a couple
minutes.
So, the video that you'll watch today is
very near and dear to my heart. I've
been making history documentaries here
on YouTube for over 10 years and
actually 12 years ago is one of my very
first history documentaries on the
Battle of Cannae. So, here we go full
circle 12 years on. Now, back in the day
I was heavily inspired by the work of
Adrian Goldsworthy. He is my muse. He's
the reason why I got into history. Very
much the way he made history
approachable and engaging is what
inspired me to try and do the same, but
in a video format. Now, when we were
doing so early on I was using Google
Earth, you know, my primitive use of
Photoshop and then using heavily the
engine of Rome: Total War.
Now, 12 years on I think we've shown in
this video leaps and strides how far
we've come. So, on a technical side, you
know, Unreal Engine has been great to
master especially with a team that I
have behind my back, dialing up that
realism, getting a lot closer to
history, and making it much more
understandable, approachable. We can do
this POV stuff that you'll enjoy.
Another cool thing is that my muse,
Adrian Goldsworthy, is no longer just
trapped in the book here, but he's with
us in the video. I got the chance to,
you know, speak to him, collaborate with
him, and so that's been awesome to have
him on the program for me on a personal
level, uh but then also for him as well,
you know, he's been, you know, 10 years
on, able to now reflect more on his
discoveries as a researcher, as a
historian, and shed new lights and
insight on this topic. So, overall, you
know, this video is sort of
quintessential in terms of what it means
for me to be on YouTube making these
documentaries.
Now, we've done a lot more stuff in the
past, and I hope to be here 10 years on.
But, admittedly, we are facing a lot of
headwinds. You'll see this across the
YouTube space when it comes to
educational and history channels. When
it comes to things like AI, uh what that
means for production, competition of
viewer attention, discoverability, how
sponsors and money gets thrown in the
mix. Suffice to say, we are in a tough
spot. Uh myself financially, we've been
kind of struggling on the channel. Uh
so, I've never been one to really, you
know, beg for views, beg for money. Uh I
will find ways to keep sustaining the
channel so that I can keep making these
documentaries, and check in with you
guys 10 years on. But, I do want to say
every little bit does count. So, please
subscribe, like the video, become a
YouTube member, uh join us on Patreon,
and especially, you know, just grab
something on our store. I made all these
little custom mugs that have history
memes built into them. I hope you enjoy
them, and we have some cool stuff that
we've commissioned over the years from
artists like this map of Carthage that I
have myself in my home that I think
you'll appreciate. So, no matter what
you choose to do, I can't thank you
enough for the support over the years,
uh whether you've been watching us for
decades, or for the last couple years,
or even just in this video. Thank you so
much for staying along, you know,
supporting human-made work, supporting
history, and yeah, again, I can't thank
you guys enough, and enjoy the video.
I'll see you in the next one.
>> Modeling the Battle of Cannae in true
size is a gargantuan undertaking.
While we shall be presenting our
reconstruction, other interpretations
exist.
In acknowledgement of this fact, it will
be best to begin by describing the key
assumptions of our model.
First, we can begin in the abstract with
the army sizes.
Here, Polybius tells us [music] that the
Romans deployed 16 legions, eight Roman
and eight allied, which in total
numbered 80,000 infantry and roughly
6,000 cavalry.
Assuming an average distribution of
soldiers, we find [music] that each
legion has 5,000 men with the following
breakdown of troop types.
At the smallest level, this means each
century, with the exception of the
triarii, has on average 73 men.
A roughly 20% increase over the 60 men
who were part of the usual muster.
Such inflated figures are in keeping
with the idea that the army had [music]
been deliberately supersized by Rome in
an attempt to out-muscle Hannibal.
The cavalry, [music] on the other hand,
were proportionately much smaller,
consisting of but 7.5% of the total
troop count.
This was due to recent losses and the
difficulty of finding sufficient mounts
on such short notice.
Breaking out these riders, we have
assumed [music]
each Roman legion masters 10 turmae of
30 troopers for a total of 2,400
cavalry.
This leaves us with a remainder of
[music] 3,600 for the allies, which
roughly tracks with Livy's sources
claiming the allies had [music] provided
twice as many horsemen.
The entire force is under the command of
consuls Paullus [music] and Varro with
command alternating each day.
On the Carthaginian side, Polybius tells
us that Hannibal deployed 40,000
infantry and 10,000 cavalry making their
size 58% that of the Romans.
Beyond this, we have but informed
speculation to go on.
Based on accounts of prior battles in
the campaign, we shall assume the
following distribution of infantry
units.
Though [music] greatly outnumbered by
their Roman equivalents, these are
well-seasoned veteran troops who have
also been able to upgrade their gear
through the spoils of victory.
As for the cavalry, we will assume 4,000
are Gallic, 2,000 are Iberian, and 4,000
are Numidian.
In this singular category, does Hannibal
actually outnumber his foe
>> [music]
>> with 66% more riders?
This will prove to have grave
consequences.
Taken altogether, we see that there are
in total 136,000
troops accounted for.
An insanely large army which was even
more numerous when we consider the
likely presence of thousands more
support forces and camp [music]
followers.
Now, let us transport the armies to the
battlefield of Cannae.
But, to do so requires knowing exactly
where that is. It's a rather thorny
issue for any attempted recreations of
the battle.
To offer insights on this matter, we can
now turn to Dr. Adrian Goldsworthy.
>> [music]
>> The sources for Cannae are pretty good
for a battle in the ancient world, and
we can narrow down the location fairly
well. We know where the ancient town of
Cannae was.
Beyond that, everything gets a little
bit more difficult. Our best sources
tell us about the orientation of the
armies in relation to the river
Aufidius.
The problem is that this river is on a
wide, fairly flat plain and moves, moves
regularly. I visited the site when I was
doing research for my books in the late
'90s. I took with me all the maps I
could find from various uh scholarly
analyses, some of them dating back to
the 19th century, some of them 20th
century. I also had a modern Italian
uh road map of the area, the biggest I
could find.
And when I came there, the first thing
that struck me was that A, the river was
in a different position on each of these
[music] maps, but also the river I could
see in front of me on that um summer's
afternoon
was again on a different line to all the
maps that I had. It just emphasized how
much the river moves across this flood
plain, which then means that trying to
understand if, uh as I argue, the battle
did occur between the river and the hill
on which the town of Cannae stood, just
how much space there was. How wide was
this plain, and was it possible that you
could actually fit these very large
armies into that space? So, there are
lots of problems with Cannae that nature
doesn't help with.
There hasn't been any archaeology that
we could really establish the
battlefield, even if that's possible.
You have to be lucky to find the right
things. There are talk There's talk of
earlier finds, but they may be confused
with medieval battles fought near there
as well. We can't narrow down where the
river was in 216 BC. So, there's a lot
of guesswork involved, which is why
looking in this way and mapping in this
way and doing everything to scale is
absolutely invaluable. So, I argue for
the battle being fought between the
river and the hill on which the town of
Cannae stands. This would mean that this
is in a very confined space.
At the most, we're talking about a width
of about 3 km from the hill to the
river.
Um so, is it the maximum 3 km for a
battle line? That's assuming they go
straight at sort of 90° between the two.
If there's more of an angle, then things
are different. Um
so, this would mean that this was a very
dense, crowded, narrow battlefield. For
me, that makes sense. The day before,
the Romans had declined an offer of
battle from Hannibal to the north of the
river. Now, the land there is very open.
There are no features on which to rest
your flanks. There's a lot more space.
Hannibal's got better cavalry than the
Romans. He's got more of it than the
Romans. In previous battles, those
cavalry have swept around the flanks and
enveloped the Roman [music] line. So,
the Romans know they don't want that to
happen. The Romans have got tons of
infantry. Their infantry has done well,
has broken through the center [music]
at Trebia, at Trasimene. So, for me, it
makes sense. Fight somewhere narrow and
restricted where, although you won't be
able to deploy your numbers [music]
initially to the full, nevertheless,
they can't be outflanked. The great
strength of your army is protected, and
you deliver a sledgehammer blow straight
at the middle of Hannibal's line. So,
for me, that makes sense. And the fact
that it is narrow is actually an
argument in favor, rather than argument
against it.
On the other hand, some scholars have
argued that well, this is far too
narrow. And of course, depending on
where the river actually was, you might
not have 3 km, [music] you might not
have 2 km, you might have even less. In
which case, the arguments for this
become less and less likely. They've
tended to position it to the south of
the town or to the east of the hill with
the town.
So, that you still have the river on the
same flanks of the army, but there is
much more open country. There's nothing
really to anchor the Roman left, the
Carthaginian right in the same way that
you're between a river and a hill if
you're in the other position.
This has the advantage of space. There's
plenty of room for everybody.
Disadvantages of this, however, one is
that um
why fight here? How is this different
from the land north of the river where
there's plenty of open space? So, why
would the Romans be willing to fight
here when they hadn't been willing to
fight somewhere else? And why bother to
cross the river? You could have just
challenged for battle on the north bank
if that's what you wanted to do where
Hannibal had offered it before.
The other thing is when I visited the
site, I walked back having um got a lift
down to to Cannae. I walked back cuz I
wanted to look at this ground. And the
there is a very clear, very definite
slope down from the hill around Cannae
towards the coast. [music]
So, if you had deployed in this area,
one thing is that the Carthaginian
deployment and where the units were
would have been more obvious to see
because they would be deployed up a
slope and any troops behind in reserve
hidden like the Libyans would have been
easier to see [music] perhaps. And
again,
um you can argue about that. The other
thing is the Romans would have been
attacking uphill. And even a slight
advantage like this on a fairly gentle
slope is something that ancient armies
take great trouble to avoid. So, for
that reason, I don't [music] I just
don't buy this. But, it's not a case
that you can prove either way. And
again, coming to test things is okay
with this number of people in this sort
of formation, how much space do they
take? That's the great advantage of
experiments like this.
>> As you can see, even the foremost
historians on the matter are unable to
draw definitive conclusions.
Given the results of our upcoming
simulations on the army formations, we
[music] find it more probable that the
battle took place along the eastern
plains.
But, regardless [music] of the exact
placement of the armies, many of the
observations from this [music]
simulation of Cannae will apply to
either hypothesis.
With that being said, [music] let us now
proceed.
Given the aforementioned uncertainties
of the exact battle lines, we are lucky
to at least be able to work [music] off
the known location of the town of
Cannae, whose ruins can still be seen
today.
This is where we will begin our tour.
It is late July in 216 BC.
The hot summer sun beats down upon the
dry lands of Apulia as the seasonal
Volturnus blows in from the south.
Where Roman farmers once ruled these
lands, now Hannibal is their master.
Over the past few weeks, the great Punic
general has laid claim to the site
whilst campaigning in the Apulia region
of southern Italy as part of his daring
invasion of Roman territory during the
Second Punic War.
The town of Cannae itself holds
strategic value as a large supply depot
with a defensible position atop a
ridgeline hill.
As you can see, it has a commanding view
of the surrounding plains, which are
filled with open farmland.
Also of note is the Aufidus River to the
north, which lazily winds its way across
the gently sloping landscape towards the
coast of the Adriatic Sea, some 8 km to
the northeast.
Though Hannibal controls the town, his
army is too large to fit inside.
Thus, he initially sets up camp outside,
likely atop the nearby high ground.
From here, he can still survey the area,
whilst also maintaining ready access to
the river, from which he can draw fresh
water for thirsty men and horses.
Within a few days, he observes dust
clouds to the north from the vast Roman
army, which has been shadowing his every
move.
Setting off in this direction, we see
that several kilometers away, the
consuls have established their own camp
on the opposite side of the river.
Here, they too can draw from its waters
to refresh the troops.
Circling the camp, we can marvel at its
immense size. Housing over 100,000 men,
each side of its perimeter easily
measures over a kilometer across.
This is a city on the move.
The sheer scale means that it cannot
stay in one place for long without
suffering supply issues.
Thus, to mitigate these problems and to
secure access to the river, a second,
smaller camp is built on the other side
of the Aufidus.
But, such measures can only delay the
inevitable.
Soon, the consuls will have to relocate,
either to engage the Carthaginians or to
continue avoiding them.
Hannibal is well aware of this fact and
wants a fight on this ground.
To press the issue, he now moves his
camp to the same side of the river as
the main Roman position.
Doing so would have taken the greater
part of a day.
Flying to this new camp, we see that it
is somewhat smaller than that of the
legions, but no less impressive in size.
It too remains tethered to the river and
must deal with issues of supply.
Thus, as both sides now face off, they
are up against a logistical ticking
clock.
But who will make the first move?
Historically, scenarios such as this
evolve into a psychological game between
generals.
Naturally, both sides wish to fight with
the most advantages stacked up on their
side before committing to an engagement.
A large factor to consider is that each
army has already dug in and will be at
an advantage if the foe is forced to
charge into their defenses.
But on the flip side, to remain passive
in this manner betrays a lack of
confidence both to the enemy and to
one's own soldiers.
This can be even more important [music]
as morale, after all, is what can win or
lose a fight.
Thus, commanders will often deploy
troops in the open ground as a
performative offering of battle.
How far forward such battle lines are
drawn is an additional barometer of an
army's confidence.
In this case, it is Hannibal who first
offers battle on August 1st.
Paullus, supposedly the more cautious of
the two Roman consuls, holds command and
refuses out of an apparent fear that the
open ground here will be to the greater
advantage of the enemy's more numerous
cavalry.
Hannibal capitalizes on this morale
boost with another ploy to gain an
advantage.
He now sends the Numidians across the
river to chase off Roman foragers.
Despite the nearby presence of both
camps, they are impotent to prevent the
harassment.
It is another humiliating blow to the
legions.
Thus, as the more impetuous consul Varro
prepares to take command the following
day, he has been sufficiently goaded to
make an aggressive countermove.
At dawn on the 2nd of August, 216 BC, a
red vexillum is raised outside the tent
of commander Varro.
This is a traditional signal that battle
is to be given.
However, we must imagine that the troops
had more advanced notice than to wake up
to such a sign.
Orders would have been distributed the
night before to the military tribunes
and the prefecti of the army, whose job
it was to disseminate the command down
the ranks and to supervise its
execution.
Thus, as the sun rises, it lights upon
the massing ranks of infantry formations
>> [music]
>> already assembling into their unit
columns along the open ground of the
intervalum.
From here, they will be guided out one
behind the other in a procession leading
out to the battlefield.
As the great coiled snake of the Roman
army slowly unfurls,
its immense size is evidenced by the
laborious nature of the process.
Arranged in column, it takes each legion
roughly half an hour to simply leave
[music] the camp.
Thus, with two camps spilling forth
simultaneously from their main gates, we
can approximate that it will take the 16
legions around two to four hours to
fully emerge when accounting for
bottlenecks and other delays.
From here, their multi-kilometer-long
bodies will slither into position,
trampling through fields and splashing
through waters.
At the same time, Hannibal keeps [music]
a close watch on the Roman force.
With spies and perhaps even intercepted
deserters, he is informed of Consul
Varro's decision to offer battle.
Thus, as the direction of the enemy's
advance is revealed, the Punic commander
now directs his men to match course.
The offer for battle has been accepted.
Hannibal's army now emerges from its own
coils and slithers across the land.
As if to message his agreement to the
Romans, a massive plume of dust now
rises from the Punic camp.
From the perspective of an observer
miles away, it would appear [music]
as if the two sides were deliberately
coordinating their intentions with smoke
signals.
But, as the vast dust clouds rise higher
in the skies and slowly advance towards
one another, it is clear that a showdown
of monumental proportions is about
[music] to take place.
This is all noted by observers from Rome
who ride back to the city to report on
such tidings.
By the time they arrive, the fate of
Cannae will already have been
determined.
But now, let us race against the writing
of history to watch as it unfolds.
Along our battlefield, the units of
either side are moving into position.
By tradition, this takes place by first
sending out a screen of light troops to
cover the deployment of the main body.
At Cannae, such a maneuver involves the
mobilization of some 25 to 30,000
skirmishers.
A prodigious amount of troops whose
numbers alone would rival the largest
battles of the medieval era.
Here, they are but a holding force.
Behind the skirmisher screen, the battle
lines are drawn.
This process involves the army columns
marching to the extreme ends of the
formation and falling into line.
It is a simple process of
follow-the-leader, which can be executed
by even the most green troops.
However, regardless of simplicity,
deployments of this scale take time, and
it can be many more hours before the
last of the troops trickle in.
From the ground level, it is entirely
unclear to any of the participants what
is going on beyond their immediate
vicinity.
They must simply trust in the process
while officers ride back and forth to
coordinate the movements of a blind
Goliath.
Luckily for us, we can observe the
entire battlefield from above.
This is a view never experienced before
and [music] thus never documented.
As a result, our presentation is
speculative reconstruction based on
vague, myopically [music] constrained
sources.
For some insight into the nuances of
this reconstructive [music] process, we
can turn once more to military historian
Dr. Adrian Goldsworthy.
>> Now, as is always the case with the
ancient world, we don't have too much
information about what was normal, what
was typical, whether there was a
standard formation for the manipula or
whether it rather depended on
circumstances and the ground where you
were fighting.
Um
but the suggestion that they're many
times deeper than they're wide rather
suggests that that wasn't true and that
they were shallower under normal
circumstances.
Beyond that though, we don't have any
details. So, just how narrow, how deep
and how narrow were the gaps between
individual manipules? [music]
There's a whole debate about the
checkerboard formation and whether the
gaps between manipules closed up when
the fighting actually began or not.
Um
but in this case, clearly the gaps are
made significantly smaller. Therefore,
there's less need for that, there's less
requirement for that.
Just how you do it would depend and
remember
all of this is going to be guesswork.
So, we assume that because he talks
about the the units that which we
normally translate as manipules as being
there, you kept with the normal triplex
the three lines of hastati, principes,
and triarii and that each individual
manipule was narrower fronted, deeper,
and closer together with its neighbors
on either side. And presumably the
Latins that are on either flank and the
ally are doing much the same thing.
But again, precisely what that means
most ancient authors assume we know this
sort of stuff. There's no need to tell
or explain, therefore they don't bother.
And the technical manuals, if they
existed, have not survived. So, that a
lot of things we assume about ancient
warfare, you will often hear said and
I've written it [music]
um that the the standard depth, the
typical depth of a Greek phalanx, was
eight deep. Um there's very little
evidence for that, really very very
little and none at all for the Roman
army of this period as [music] to just
what's going on.
>> When it comes to reconstructing Cannae
specifically, we have founded our model
upon the better understood dynamics
[music]
of the Roman army.
At a high level, we are confident from
our sources [music]
that it consists of the allied cavalry
to the east, the infantry in the center,
and the Roman cavalry in the west.
Zooming in begins to reveal some of the
uncertainties.
The infantry, for instance, here
consists of just 14 legions with the
assumption that two entire legions have
been left behind in camp in keeping with
Polybius's claim that 10,000 troops were
held back to guard the baggage and
threaten the enemy's camp.
Zooming in closer, we see that the
individual legions still maintain their
multi-layered formation of infantry
tiers, [music] but have arranged
themselves in a deep, tight formation
rather than the more typical
checkerboard pattern.
This is an interpretation of Polybius's
report that the maniples were, quote,
closer together than usual and [music]
many times deeper than they were wide.
Here, we have assumed a total legionary
depth of 50 men, though some scholars
push [music] this to an excess of 70
men.
In either case, using [music] standard
troop spacing and accounting for gaps
between units, we end up with a total
depth of around 100 m for the heavy
infantry.
This is an extremely unorthodox
formation in light of the fact that most
armies of the period drew up in files of
four to eight men or 10 to 20 m deep.
The reason being that while depth
improves staying power, each added rank
yields diminishing returns.
Any extra manpower is better used to
extend [music] that unit's width with
which to outflank one's foe.
But at Cannae, the Romans have more than
enough manpower to spare.
Already,
>> [music]
>> the infantry span almost 2 km in width.
By going deeper, the consuls apparently
wish to ensure that their green [music]
troops are as insulated as possible from
morale shocks.
Dropping down to the ground [music]
perspective of a soldier in the midst of
this formation, it is easy to see its
psychological advantages.
To all sides, one is surrounded by
comrades, while the front lines are
nearly [music] a soccer field away.
All this means that the vast majority of
Roman troops
>> [music]
>> can expect to do nothing more than stand
in line and let the sheer weight of
their ranks [music]
brute force its way to victory.
If they are lucky, they might catch a
glimpse of the action along the front.
Zooming back [music] out, we can now
turn our attention to the cavalry.
The nature of their formations are even
[music] less well understood, as will be
emphasized by Dr. Goldsworthy.
>> When you come to cavalry, you have to
think in a very different way to
infantry, and that's quite hard for us
to do because most of us
don't necessarily know much about
horses. We're certainly not used to
horses in these sorts of numbers. You
don't see thousands of cavalrymen
anywhere in the world today. So, even
the big parades and the ceremonial units
you have, you know, they're not on that
sort of scale. And when movies have
extras mounted, they never have those
sorts of numbers. And of course, these
days they'll be adding lots of extra CGI
horsemen. So, the the big blocks of
Rohirrim you see in the Pelennor Fields
in The Return of the King movie, they
look very visually impressive, but that
is not the way any real cavalry would
operate.
Because the whole point of cavalry is
speed, maneuverability,
uh movement. They are not like
infantrymen who will go forward and
perhaps best go forward slowly and then
slog it out with the enemy. They'll
charge, the enemy will run, or they will
be [music] chased back. You chase them
till you start to get scattered, you
start to get blown, they have reserves,
then they chase you back, your reserve
chase them back, and so on. Ancient
authors characterized cavalry warfare as
incredibly fluid, back and forth, quite
hard to understand. And exactly the same
pattern was still visible in the 18th
and 19th century. You know, you could
read about Waterloo, and it's exactly
the same there. That's the way lots of
horses behave. So, it's best not to
think of big, big blocks similar to the
infantry when we come to cavalry. And
probably we're thinking more of troop
squadrons, individual units forming
several lines but with large gaps
between them [music] to allow this
maneuverability, to allow this
flexibility, because you pack lots of
horses closely together, and you're just
going to end up with a big stampede
either forward or backwards, but
something you can't control. Witness the
defeat of the Pompeian cavalry at
Pharsalus, where several thousand of
them were stampeded by a relatively
small number of infantry.
And they can't recover from that. And
the less trained the horses are, the
more important it is to keep them in
separate blocks and separate units, cuz
they just get excited, and they they're
inclined to run in the same direction as
everybody else.
So, you have to think of groups of
30 men like the Roman turma, 40, 50,
100, maybe 200. Units like that,
>> [music]
>> but lots of them and in more than one
line. And that's a very different way of
thinking about how these would be
deployed to our standard nice little
rectangle on a map where this represents
500, 1,000, 5,000 men. With cavalry in
particular, you shouldn't think that way
for for but with cavalry, it's fatal to
think that way. They need lots more
space. Polybius talks about cavalrymen
requiring double the amount of frontage
that infantry of the same numbers would
require.
But, it's not quite as simple as oh,
there's a you know, you just spread them
out and each cavalryman requires twice
the space. It's the units require space
around them. So, that's what matters.
We've got to think of lots of little
blocks, little bit like some of those
17th century woodcuts and engravings of
English Civil War battles and that sort
of thing.
>> With these ideas in mind, our model
assumes that the Roman cavalry are
compactly deployed in their 30-men
turmae, with separation between rows of
units to [music] allow for the more
fluid engagement of mounted troops.
As such, their frontage is about 600 m
across and 70 m deep.
Flipping to the other side, we can now
examine the disposition of the
Carthaginians.
Here, there is very little precedent to
draw upon for their reconstruction.
Thus, our model largely relies on
matching the width of their Roman
counterparts and adding depth to reach
the troop counts given to us by our
sources.
Namely, this includes the roughly 4,000
Numidian cavalry under Hanno on the
eastern flank,
Gallic and Iberian cavalry under
Hasdrubal
on the western flank,
and the 35,000 infantry
under Hannibal and Mago in the center.
Of this last group, we have assumed that
approximately [music]
5,000 troops have been left back at camp
to counter Rome's own 10,000 troops,
>> [music]
>> which were siphoned off to threaten
their baggage train.
Diving deeper, we can now explore
[music] the infantry.
It is here that Hannibal uses the
non-Punic troops to form his famous
crescent [music]
at the start of battle.
Typical media depictions tend to
over-exaggerate its shape without
accounting [music] for the
practicalities of such a formation.
In reality, [music] it is likely that
the battle line consisted of an eclectic
mix of small war bands of around 200 to
500 men,
which were arranged in echelon, one next
to the other.
In theory, each unit [music] might
advance further out than its neighbor to
increase the overall bowing of the line.
However, they would have been hesitant
to advance too far and expose their
flanks.
Thus, by assuming that each unit
overlaps significantly with its
neighbor, our model results in a
crescent [music] with a maximum depth of
a mere 85 m at the center.
Given that the frontage of the infantry
is almost 2 km across, this is an
exceptionally shallow crescent.
Such a finding begins to cast [music]
doubt on traditional understandings
regarding the purpose and function of
the crescent at Cannae.
This should be discussed [music] further
when we simulate the actual combat along
this front.
For more thoughts on the matter, we can
turn once more to Dr. Goldsworthy.
>> Anything that's unique is always harder
to study because there aren't parallels.
And there's nothing quite like this, you
know, there've been various theories
that the naval battle of Ecnomus had
similar tactics to Cannae and all this
sort of thing, but none of them really
hold any any water or any weight. They
just don't don't make sense. It's better
to see this not as a plan that Hannibal
had in the back of his mind for years
and oh, I've got this cunning idea, but
something tailored to his army in
relation to the Roman army and where he
was fighting and the circumstances of
that battle and the build up to it, the
campaign, something that's right for
today and will work for today because
he's not doing the same thing elsewhere
and he doesn't try and do this again
anywhere else.
So, that means it's difficult. [music]
The probability is that this is rather
less dramatic and shallower than many
diagrams will show, but then diagrams
need to emphasize. [music]
So, just what was necessary. The point
clearly is that Hannibal wishes the very
center of his line to get into contact
before other parts of it. So, the very
central unit is advanced some distance.
We don't know how far, you know, is it
10 m, 100 m, more, whatever it might be.
Again, this is something that the model
can test very, very well and give us an
idea of what this would look like, but a
lot depends on how people would behave.
So, he wants the Romans to make contact
there first. Is that in the expectation
the rest of the Roman line will stop
while that's being fought and until
they're pushed back? Is it that this
will start to make the Roman line more
ragged as they begin to come forward? Uh
that some might attack, start their
charge, start their volley of missiles
at a a greater distance. We'll come on
to all of this later, but it
>> [music]
>> it's difficult to know precisely what
Hannibal intends. So, it's all a
question of experimenting. It's bound to
be shallower than the Roman formation
because you're covering the same
frontage as a far more uh numerically
superior force of Romans. There's a lot
of Romans out there. You're trying to
match their frontage. But, that also
means that it's much less dense as to
what's going on. There's more space for
not just individual units to act and
react and support each other, move back
backwards and forwards depending on how
the fighting is going, but also for
officers, commanders to move around.
>> Having covered the formation of the
non-African infantry, we can now turn
our attention to the Libyans.
Our sources are unclear on their
deployment with Livy stating vaguely,
"quote
They were used to form [music] the two
wings which had been drawn back."
Some depictions [music]
show them stacked in deep columns.
But once more we should question the
practicality of such exaggerated
deployments.
Working in true [music] size we see that
there is little benefit to having the
units so far back from [music] the
front.
At the scales we are working with any
position they might adopt locally
results in [music] the equivalent
distance required to move from the wings
towards the center or around the flanks
for an envelopment. [music]
Thus we have chosen to deploy the
Libyans at no greater depth than the
legions whose formation was already
considered overkill in terms of staying
power.
Ultimately this seems [music] to have
been their role in battle.
To hold as an unbreakable bastion
[music] of elite troops that could be
mobilized when the time came to strike
at vulnerable Roman forces.
With this in mind we can now turn to the
cavalry on the wings.
To the east we find [music] the Numidian
light cavalry.
Here we have modeled them as loosely
spaced units which can easily maneuver
for evasive skirmishing against the
enemy.
The end result is a formation of
equivalent numbers to the Roman allies
opposite them but with a greater overall
footprint.
Meanwhile on the western flank we find
the Gallic and Iberian cavalry. [music]
They number about two and a half times
that of the Romans standing against
them.
The severity of this mismatch is
reflected in our model by the idea that
while they might intend to fight as
[music] close order cavalry, their great
numbers have forced them to separate
into multiple groups
>> [music]
>> to preserve command and control and
avoid devolving into a stampeding herd.
Any one of these groups has sufficient
strength to greatly damage the Roman
cavalry on its own.
Massed in this way though, the combined
might of the Carthaginians is poised to
absolutely flatten them.
Now that we have painstakingly laid out
our model of the armies at Cannae,
we can take a step back to appreciate
the results of their true size.
Based on our assumptions, it measures
over 3 km across.
Let us now fly across the battlefield to
get a more visceral sense of the scales
[music] involved.
For a more grounded approach, we might
even consider simulating a walk across
the battlefield.
But to do so would take roughly [music]
40 minutes.
Even when simulating a horse making the
journey, it would take a rider around 5
minutes at full gallop to race from one
end to the other.
As a final measure of the battlefield
size,
we can now fire off an Napoleonic cannon
across its breadth.
As the shot arches across the
battlefield, it passes [music] by
endless ranks of soldiers.
Even under the best conditions, the
cannon's maximum range will only get us
halfway across the field.
The scales here are simply unfathomable.
Given all this, we must marvel at what
[music] it would have been like to
experience such an event where the scale
of the conflict stretches from horizon
to horizon.
For soldiers, at least they can be
resigned to focusing on the more
comprehensible scope of their immediate
surroundings.
Leaders, on the other hand, are afforded
no such luxury.
The burden [music] of commands demands
that generals and their offices must
somehow remain apprised of matters
across [music] the entire front.
>> It's going to be very hard for anybody
to see all of it. It's a big army.
You're on a fairly flat plane.
Um you don't have a vantage point. Your
two senior commanders, your consuls,
each choose to command one of the
cavalry wings to keep those in the fight
as long as possible so that the center
can win. Once they're there, they can't
see very much beyond the area
immediately around them. They can see
the enemy, but they can't see much more
than that. One of the big drawbacks of
reducing the gaps between the maniples,
making the maniples deeper, but packing
everybody into that space is that there
is less room for staff officers, senior
officers, and their
um
support staff to ride around the
formation, to ride amongst the Roman
line. It's much harder to get around.
It's also harder to see anything. So,
the command and control element is a
problem right from the very start. But
again, it comes back to this, we've got
a simple plan, all we've got to do is
go forward and eat our way into the
enemy line.
In contrast to the Romans, Hannibal has
a rather more conventional battle line.
Yes, it's got the crest and everything,
but in terms of the depth of formations,
how densely packed they are, there's no
indication he's trying to match the
Romans by cramming everybody in. His
formations are relatively shallow in
comparison to the Romans. There'll be
intervals between the units. Not just,
you know, we can see that by the fact
that he alternates Iberians and Gauls in
the center of the line. These are
clearly distinct units with some sort of
space between them. That means that he
and his brother and any other senior
officers can see better what's going on,
but can also move around. They can ride
between units. They can ride along the
battle line. They can ride behind them.
They can get to close to most of those
units and talk to them, encourage them,
set an example in a way that is much,
much more difficult for the Romans in
their far more crowded, dense formation.
>> All of this takes place in the calm
before the storm.
From here on out, the descent into the
maddening true size of Cannae
has only just begun.
It's midday on the 2nd of August, 216
BC, and the largest Roman army yet
assembled has finally finished deploying
for battle at Cannae.
Opposite them stands the far smaller
army of Hannibal Barca.
What is about to transpire will go down
as one of the most famed and studied
battles of history.
But never before has it been simulated
to this level [music] of detail.
From fleshing out the unrecorded
skirmishing action, which occupied the
bulk of the morning's action,
to the messy realities of marching
70,000 infantry through obstacle-strewn
farmland into the teeth of an echeloned
battle line,
the clashing of the cavalry across two
wildly different engagements, [music]
the maneuvering of troops in each phase
of the ensuing battle,
and the final envelopment of the Roman
army
in what would prove to be one of the
single bloodiest days of battle in
history.
We bring it all to life from both a
bird's-eye perspective
and the boots [music] on the ground.
This is the climactic conclusion of the
Battle of Cannae.
On the 2nd of August, 216 BC, a red
vexillum waved outside the tent of
Consul Gaius Terentius Varro.
After days of posturing across the
plains of Cannae, it was finally time
for battle.
But even such a simple matter would take
hours for the tens of thousands of
troops to be led out of their camps and
onto the battlefield.
As both armies deployed for battle,
their 3-km fronts were screened by a
mass of skirmishers numbering some
28,000 [music] troops in total.
An incredible host in its own right,
whose assembled ranks would have dwarfed
most battles of the medieval era.
On the Roman side came the 20,000
velites, a class of young poor levies
equipped [music] with simple javelins,
small shields, and animal skin caps.
Unlike the heavy infantry, they do not
appear to have adopted any rigid
formation or been accompanied [music] by
any formal officer rank.
Thus, they deployed as a loose swarm
with relative autonomy over their area
of the battlefield.
However, it is likely that some guidance
was needed to coordinate their actions.
Thus, we have assumed that the bands of
Velites remain relatively close to their
parent maniples.
This would have given them several
hundred meters worth of buffer.
Enough separation to perform screening
actions, but close enough to fall back
to the bastion of heavy infantry if
pressed too heavily.
Bridging this gap will likely have been
runners or mounted messengers meant to
maintain some level of coordination
between the two groups.
These, presumably, prowled the rear
lines of the Velites, keeping tabs on
their ranks and peering over their heads
in an attempt to glean some sense of the
enemy's disposition.
Opposite them stand their Carthaginian
counterparts.
At just 8,000 strong, they number less
than half that of the Romans.
Yet, what they may lack in quantity,
they more than make up for in
experience.
Among these ranks stand not poor young
boys, but mature specialists, which
include the Libyan Lonchophori,
the Iberian Caetrati,
and the Balearic Funditores.
Most are armed with bundles of javelins
and small round shields.
Yet, it is the last of these groups
which would prove most formidable.
Compared to the rest of the skirmishers,
which largely relied on short-range
weapons,
these professional mercenaries wielded
long-range slings capable of loosing
lead bullets at speeds of over 100 km/h
and ranges of up to 400 m.
Thus, as the two skirmishing bodies
drifted close to one another. They were
poised for an incredibly asymmetrical
clash.
But how exactly such fights occurred is
left a mystery, as their details are
rarely documented by our sources.
We must imagine that these were rather
fluid in nature.
Each battle line, after all, was
composed of a loose swarm, whose members
would surge in and out of no man's land
as packs or as individuals.
To better conceptualize these dynamics,
we can focus in on a small region of the
front. Here, across a space no larger
than a soccer field, are faced off 100
youths and 40 adults.
Yet, unlike a friendly game,
which might take place at the school
sporting event,
now both sides are armed with deadly
weapons with no rules or referees to
curb the violence.
For the velites, this was reportedly a
time to show one's courage in battle
before comrades and superiors.
Joining them on the front lines, we see
what it might have looked like to step
forth into the fray.
Here, we observe a mass of the enemy
before us,
just beyond the reach of our weapons.
To strike them will require leaving the
safety of our ranks.
In a fit of courage, a young soldier
might dash out to taunt the foe, dancing
between incoming salvos, and toss their
own javelin before pulling back.
Others might more timidly emerge to
collect spent weapons on the ground or
pass them ahead to the more deserving.
Likewise, the enemy does the same,
though with greater strength and
practiced accuracy.
As this dance is repeated over the early
hours of battle.
We must imagine that rivalries would
have formed as each group of skirmishers
tested itself against the other across
their slice of the battlefield.
In areas where both sides are armed with
javelins, perhaps there would have been
a relative balance between the more
numerous Roman youths and the more
experienced Carthaginian adults.
In other areas, perhaps a slight
advantage was gained by one side or the
other due to
of the terrain or as injuries and deaths
began to take their toll on the morale
of the participants.
Yet, now imagine what would have
happened in areas where these same
groups of javelin-armed velites were
matched against the professional
slingers of the Balearic Isles.
Here, the youths would have been met
with the ancient equivalent of gunfire.
Lead bullets fired at extreme range with
such force that it could pierce armor
and such accuracy that it could
reportedly target individual parts of
the face.
The ensuing carnage is left to our
imagination.
Of our two primary sources, Livy is mute
on the matter while Polybius merely
remarks, "Quote,
the affair between these light-armed
troops was indecisive."
Clearly, this skips over the very real
life or death struggles which transpired
in the earliest hours of the Battle of
Cannae.
But, without further information, we
[music] must move on.
At some point, the skirmishing phase was
called off by the waving of banners and
the blaring of trumpets.
Likely, this occurred as the last of the
heavy infantry and cavalry had reached
[music] their designated places in the
battle line.
By now, it would have been close to
midday with the sun beating down on the
sweating brows of over 120,000
idling [music] soldiers.
The heat and their nerves left them
dripping with anticipation to get this
over with.
Soon, this wish would be granted by the
commanders who deemed it time for the
battle to begin in earnest.
Our sources claim that it was Hannibal
who made the first move, sending forth
his 10,000 cavalry against the Roman
flanks.
This would have begun at a walk or slow
trot so as to maintain stamina and unit
cohesion. Thus, crossing the roughly
half kilometer separating the armies
would have taken around 3 to 5 minutes.
For a better idea of what this may have
looked like, we can zoom in, beginning
on the western flank.
Here, the hooves of 6,000 Gallic and
Iberian horses kick up large plumes of
dust into the air.
It is an impressive force whose sheer
size has forced them to break out into
multiple waves of assault and reserve
units just to squeeze into the narrow
battlefield between the infantry and the
river.
When these units get closer [music] to
the Romans, the first of their ranks
will begin to pick up speed.
Officers shout encouragement to their
squadmates while steeds vocalize their
own emotions to the herd.
As momentum builds, each individual is
now swept along in a growing avalanche,
enveloped by deafening sound and
blinding dust.
To participate in such a charge must
have been an incredible rush of
adrenaline.
The more than twice outnumbered ranks of
the equites have taken a defensive
posture alongside the river.
>> Do not concern yourself with those
Carthaginians yonder.
Few will be honest sons of Carthage, if
there is such a thing.
Carthaginians, cowards all, pay others
to die for them.
Let us give them death.
>> Livy's account claims that around this
time, the consul Paulus dismounted after
being wounded by a slinger, leading many
other Romans to do the same.
Though this is not backed up by other
sources, it does perhaps preserve some
tradition of cavalry having chosen to
fight on foot in an attempt to bolster
their static position.
Whatever the case, it seems clear that
the Romans were indeed aware that they
were doomed to be defeated on this
flank.
It was just a matter of delaying the
inevitable as long as possible for the
infantry to win the day.
To get a true sense of things, we can
drop down to the front lines.
Here, the coming of the Carthaginians is
heralded by rising dust clouds and the
crescendo of hoof beats. Soon, this is
followed by the haunting appearance of a
dark line rolling swiftly over the
countryside.
For a soldier in the center of
formation, observing this
horizon-spanning avalanche of flesh and
iron will have shaken them to the core.
The dire nature of Rome's predicament is
only further reinforced as we zoom out
to see that beyond this first wave of
Carthaginians are two more great waves
of death hurtling towards them.
To make matters worse, we are told by
Polybius that unlike typical cavalry
engagements,  there was none of
the usual formal advance and retreat.
But when they once got to close
quarters, they grappled man-to-man and
dismounting from their horses fought on
foot.
In our model, we have depicted this as a
literal smashing together of the front
ranks.
From a distance, this is relatively easy
to conceptualize as it aligns with the
way such engagements are typically shown
in games and movies.
However, it proves far harder to imagine
the realities on the ground.
Here would have been a roughly 500-m
wide rolling mass of man and beast.
Unlike the infantry blocks which can be
expected to have some level of rigidity
in their fighting, the cavalry were
entirely more fluid given the inherent
nature of being mounted upon animals.
In some cases, man and horse worked
together to fight with some semblance of
coordination.
Other times, a rider was at the mercy of
their steeds' unpredictable motions.
All the while, slashes, stabs, and
javelin throws were being exchanged.
Brute force even had its place as riders
reportedly resorted to physically
dragging each other off the saddle.
On the ground would have been strewn the
carnage of trampled men, crippled
horses, spent weapons, and dismounted
troops who now waded through the mayhem.
Understandably, the fighting would have
been brutal.
Our sources claim that the Romans fought
with great spirits and determination.
However, the numerical odds were stacked
heavily against them.
It was only a matter of time before the
crushing might of the Carthaginians
broke through.
But for now, let us pivot over to the
eastern flank.
Here, we find an entirely different
dynamic at play.
On this front, the Carthaginians have
deployed the 4,000 Numidian light
cavalry.
Specializing in hit-and-run tactics,
these troops will have surged out
towards the Roman line in nimble
squadrons.
Once in range, they then loosed their
javelins before wheeling about.
From the Roman perspective,
this would not have been as immediately
deadly as the [music] brutal charge on
the western flank. Yet, it was
nonetheless extremely [music] trying on
the nerves.
The refusal of the enemy to come to
blows denied the equites a chance to
relieve stress through violence.
Instead, they were subjected to an
incessant needling.
From a ground's-eye view, we can see how
unnerving this would have been.
Yet, any attempts to break ranks and
chase after the Numidians would have had
the effect of chasing after a flock of
birds.
Lighter and faster, they simply darted
out of the way and into the unknown
dangers of the [music] dust-shrouded
ground beyond.
Over pursuing in such a situation would
have tired out one's steed and
potentially left Romans isolated. At
this point, Numidian squadrons would
have closed in to pick them off.
Such tactics would have been enabled by
the use of multiple self-reinforcing
ranks of reserves, behind which
skirmishers could rally and relieve one
another.
In this way, might the fighting be
dragged out for hours.
Thus, we see the highly dynamic nature
of the eastern flank, which slowly but
inexorably sapped the strength of the
Romans.
As the fighting on the flanks occurred,
>> [music]
>> it was now the turn of the Romans to
take the offensive by advancing their
main body of heavy infantry.
Once more, it should be emphasized that
even such a seemingly simple maneuver
was made complex by the sheer scale of
the task at hand.
After all, we are talking about
coordinating the actions of 70,000
individuals across a roughly 2-km wide
front.
For more on the matter, we can turn to
historian Adrian Goldsworthy.
>> Once you've got your army in position,
you also have to, once you're ready,
decide to order it forward. We don't get
any specifics about this. We assume that
it's done by signal,
um,
in that you have trumpets blowing,
standards perhaps move, the commander's
standard moved in a particular way, or
maybe just the the trumpet signal that
is then taken up by trumpeters along the
line, and everybody goes.
Um, it's [music] probably not as neat
and everyone stepping off at exactly the
same time on the same foot sort of
thing. Again, this is a a big,
inexperienced army, bigger than anything
the Romans have ever known before. So,
nobody really knows how to do things.
You're trying to modify your normal
practices as little as possible to keep
everybody understanding what's going on.
Um, in later periods in the 1st century
BC, we hear at, uh, Philippi, Brutus
sends out dispatch riders to give the
order to advance to all different
elements of his army, and as a result,
various legions, each one goes when it
gets the order and just heads off, so
that the ones that are nearest to him
get theirs first and start the attack
first, and the others come in later. And
you you know, clearly his staff of this
fairly amateur Civil War army had not
worked out that this was a likely to to
happen.
Um at Thapsus, one of Caesar's battles,
where the advance begins [music] without
his instructions, Caesar was trying to
stop them, and one cohort persuades
forces [music] its trumpeter, its
cornicen, to signal the order to advance
and starts going, and then the order is
taken up, everybody repeats the signal,
and everybody goes, and Caesar is
supposed to say "All right, fair enough,
get on with it." and attack. So,
even with the more professional armies
of that period, literally in a Civil War
situation, you could get moments of
confusion. So, it's again, we've got
these nice digital figures representing
our
our Roman soldiers, but remember,
everybody's an individual, everybody's a
human being, and this is not the most
experienced Roman army around.
>> But, if the start of an advance was
already messy, the march itself proved
even more so.
This had much to do with the inherent
variability of the participants, the
terrain, and the conditions.
For much of our model, we've been forced
to simplify such variables.
But, in this section, we shall attempt
to dial up the realism to give you a
better idea of the real experience.
Here, Dr. Goldsworthy shall once more be
our guide.
>> As the Romans move forward, their
formations will start to decay, at least
to some extent. Important thing to
remember is that even though Cannae is
fought in what we consider to be a flat
plain, in that there are no major
terrain features recorded in our sources
or obvious from the ground today, and
that's true wherever it takes place,
whichever of the theories is followed,
that real landscapes, particularly
farmland, are not like
carefully mown football pitches [music]
or bowling greens or anything like that.
This is real land, so it won't be
perfectly flat. There will be little
undulations. There'll be little humps
and bumps because it's farmland. People
have been using this. There's going to
be tracks. There's going to be walls.
There's going to be boundary stones.
There are going to be perhaps hedges,
trees, vines in places. We don't know
what was being grown there at the time
of the battle. What the
um but there could be animal pens. There
could be drainage ditches. All of these
things and you know people have been
very clear farmers marking out this is
mine. This is yours and that's the
boundary you don't cross. So, all of
these things will mean that not
everybody is going to be going at a
perfectly steady regular pace
straightforward. People will tend to
veer a bit to the right, a bit to the
left.
Some groups will move faster than
others. You get the very keen officer
who's urging people forward who always
half anticipates, goes too soon. The
other who's a bit sluggish, who's a bit
slower, a bit more cautious.
Um So, the little bits of the micro
landscape in a sense that we can't
represent. We've got no chance to all
even if we locate the battlefield
knowing what this was and would never
appear in a an account by a Polybius or
Livy or anyone like this because it it
mattered to the dozen or so men who were
marching along that bit of frontage and
those behind them. It doesn't matter to
anybody else. Many people would never
know it was there at all. You know,
there might be the odd building out
there, the odd hut as well. Who knows
what was there?
Um fences, anything, you know, lots of
things like this. So, [music]
it's going to get messy fairly quickly.
This is human nature. Added to the
stress of all this, you are advancing
towards an enemy that you can see and
that is waiting to kill you or perhaps
soon coming forward to kill you. And
even however keen you are, this is
still, you know, pretty nervous moment
for anyone. With all the excitement, the
noise, the
the hubbub of all those people and the
sense of again,
being with this army is probably the
time when you're seeing more [music]
human beings in any one place than you
ever have before. When that army raises
its battle cry, it's probably louder
than anything you've heard in your life
before, particularly for many of the
Romans and the less experienced ones.
So, this is a very novel situation. As
the Romans advance, there isn't a great
deal that their officers can do.
The consuls are off on the flanks. Um
the
centurions
two with each maniple in theory, six
tribunes with a legion. They can
influence the men immediately around
them, uh anyone who can hear their
voice, and then it is willing to listen
to it. It's mainly a question they can
try and keep the pace steady. They can
try and stop people from surging forward
too quickly, breaking up formation even
faster than it's it's going to happen.
They can try and encourage them. They
can try and cheer them. Polybius talks
about the Roman lines, Roman troops
regularly advancing, cheering, and
banging their weapons against their
shields.
>> [music]
>> So, if you've got that sort of noise,
then it's all the harder for officers to
compete with that, for trumpet signals
to compete with that. But again, think
of the volume you might get from the
crowd at a sporting event, the the
cheering, the chanting you can have.
It's that sort of volume of noise. So,
the Romans can't do a lot apart from
keep everybody moving forward, try and
keep them in some sort of order and
fairly steady, but they're not doing
anything very, very clever. And there
are limits, again comes back to this
dense formation that's going to be
deteriorating even further, for anyone
on horseback that gives them a bit of a
viewpoint higher than everyone else.
It's going to be hard to move around the
battle line because there's [music] not
the space there would normally be
between maniples.
Even in the approach to combat. So, all
of these things restrict what they can
do, but they can certainly encourage
each other and try and keep things
reasonably steady. In contrast, the
Carthaginian commanders have a more
normal deployment. Hannibal, his brother
Mago, who's there in the center of the
line. They can ride around. They can
ride between the units. They can ride up
to them. They can encourage [music]
the men that um they want to as far as
they can in terms of the ability to
speak the languages of the different
units involved. [music]
The Iberians in particular have been you
know, serving for a long time in the
Hannibal's family. So, they're men he
knows well. He probably can communicate
with them. The Gauls have been with him
for less than 2 years, but again, that's
you know, um
a time to build up some sort of
relationship.
So, they can do more. They can see more.
Everybody's going to be a little bit
confused. Between the two armies, you've
got this large numbers of skirmishers
fighting their own little battle. He can
see what's going on there probably
better than the Romans can. Whether he
contributes to this at all or whether
the skirmishers and the officers with
them just do their job and they have
supports organized and all that sort of
thing, very hard to say. But, Hannibal
is in a better position than the Romans
to see what's going on, but it is still
quite difficult in a battle of this size
for any one man to be somewhere where he
can see all that's going on and be able
to respond to it.
>> Eventually, after what likely took
around 7 to 10 minutes of marching, the
leading Roman infantry units would have
come within striking range of the
Carthaginian's crescent formation.
However, its echeloned nature further
complicated the meeting of the two
armies.
Presumably, fighting would have begun
among the most protruding units where
Hannibal and his brother directly
supervised the troops.
Here, battle likely took place in the
usual manner with the Romans charging
and launching their pila at the enemy.
Likewise, the Gallic and Iberian
infantry on the receiving end of the
attack also charged at the last moment
with their own flurry of missiles.
But, what happened to either side of
this first contact point?
This is where things start to get even
more confusing with no clues offered
from our sources.
Thankfully, the true size nature of our
model can offer some insight on the
matter.
One effect may have been that the
crescent blunted the force of the usual
Roman assault.
By echeloning units backwards, we see
that as the Romans get close to the line
of first contact, the Carthaginians are
further and further away.
By the time you reach the edges of the
infantry, the gap is as large as 100 m.
For troops caught [music] up in the
momentum of the charge resonating out
from the center of the crescent, having
to cover this extra football fields
worth of ground must have impacted their
stamina and psychology.
We know this was a serious issue to
consider.
At the Battle of Pharsalus, for
instance, Caesar's troops actually
stopped mid-charge to redress their
lines when they observed the enemy was
not advancing to meet them.
On this occasion, the veteran troops
were able to halt, reform, and re-engage
for a more optimal fight.
At Cannae, however, the Roman army was
far greener and unlikely to have been
able to pull off such a feat.
Thus, the troops at the extremes of the
line were likely faced with sub-optimal
conditions.
With the extra distance [music] to
travel, did they now run and arrive
exhausted?
Did they throw their pila too early?
Did they slow down and hesitate to
engage?
Unfortunately, we simply don't know.
But, whatever occurred, the crescent
seems to have helped further delay and
disorganize the infantry attack.
A brilliant move on Hannibal's part to
counter Rome's greatest strength.
But, no matter how blunted the legions
charge may have been, the sheer weight
behind the assault meant that it was
only a matter of time before the Punic
line began to cave in.
We are told by our sources that this
occurred in the center.
Here, Livy writes, quote,
"This wedge was first driven back so far
as to straighten the front, and then,
continuing to yield, even left a hollow
in the center."
Other sources back up the idea that the
Carthaginian crescent was inverted over
the course of the fighting,
but how was this achieved?
Polybius mentions the enemy giving
ground, which serves as a convenient
explanation.
But, military historians have thrown
much doubt upon its feasibility.
After all, pulling off such a complex
maneuver was difficult enough on the
parade ground, let alone in the thick of
fighting.
Even if one could perform such a thing,
there is the problem of doing so over a
significant distance without
disintegrating into a route.
To better grasp this issue, we can
simulate what bowing the line actually
would have looked like from the ground
level.
As hundreds of meters fly by, you start
to truly understand how great [music] a
distance this is.
By the time you get to a 600 m fall back
point, you are likely further away from
the front than the [music] two armies
were from each other at the start of
battle.
Thus, no matter the mechanism of the
retreat, it seems far more plausible to
assume that any inverting of the
crescent [music]
would have been far shallower than most
diagrams would lead you to believe.
That being said, we cannot definitely
rule out a large retreat, or even a
breakthrough occurring.
But, for our model, we have assumed a
shallow inversion.
As for how this was achieved, a
controlled retreat over such a small
distance does start to seem more
plausible, especially when we [music]
reimagine what extended infantry combat
may have looked like.
This is best explained by Dr. [music]
Goldsworthy himself.
>> We do know that the Romans start to push
back the center of Hannibal's line. They
push back the crescent in the center,
perhaps break through [music] it at
least at some point. How this occurs
comes into all sorts of questions about
just how
ancient warfare, ancient core infantry
combat did actually [music] develop, did
actually happen. The Hollywood image is
everybody runs together, fights
individual jewels, and you know, nearly
everybody
from which somebody dies in all of these
things, and then somehow they know
they've won or they haven't. Um, real
life isn't like that. It's about groups.
It's about
um,
units going forward, trying to inspire
each other, officers trying to lead
them.
So, it fits more with the model that
people like Phil Sabin and I have
developed, where
you get bursts, pulses almost, of
combat, where because
hand-to-hand combat is physically
incredibly demanding and emotionally
demanding, but it's physically hard
work. You know, ask a fencer, martial
artist, boxer, someone like that how
tired they get. Even somebody as highly
trained as that after short bouts of
combat.
Then, add in the weight of weapons and
the stress that somebody's actually
trying to kill you. Then,
you can't do this for um,
10 minutes, let alone hours on end. It
will be short bouts of combat, after
which the two lines, two sides separate,
perhaps only, you know, the distance of
10 ft or so. That would make them safe,
maybe even less. If you're outside the
the distance anyone can thrust a spear
or stab with a sword, then unless
they've got something to throw at you,
you're safe while you get your breath
back, you get your um enthusiasm back,
and then you go forward again, renew the
combat. So, whether that's both sides
step back, whether that's one side steps
back, perhaps because it feels it's not
quite so confident, not doing quite so
well, you do get
>> [music]
>> mentions in ancient battles of
a side being pushed back a considerable
distance without apparently breaking and
running.
So, although that might be hard for us
to imagine, within this context, that
seems to be fairly typical of a lot of
ancient infantry combat. You've got lots
of Roman leaders encouraging them.
You've also got Hannibal, Mago, other
officers encouraging the Gauls, the
Iberians [music] to keep fighting. So,
this does It is presented as a very hard
struggle. The Romans do not simply punch
through the center quickly. This takes
time. And again, we can look at the
overall casualty rate for Hannibal's
army. It does seem very high for
victorious army, and the emphasis is
that many of your leaders [music] go.
Now, they're not all falling at this
stage, but it emphasizes how hard this
fighting is.
>> But all of this action in the center
would have taken time.
Meanwhile, the cavalry engagements,
which had begun earlier, would have been
reaching their climax.
Our sources claim that the action peaked
on the western flank first.
Here, we find that the rolling cavalry
engagement has resulted in a ragged
battle line.
This would have been particularly true
around the wings, as the more numerous
Carthaginians attempted to outflank
their prey.
Along the river's edge, such affairs
would have been complicated by the
rushing waters and muddy banks.
But certainly, there would have been
some messy fighting across such
contested ground.
Across the opposite side of the cavalry
brawl, the open fields would have
presented better [music] opportunities
for maneuver.
Here, we can imagine that cavalrymen
tentatively made their way through the
dust clouds, feeling out the edges of
the foe's formation.
Away from the pack, more isolated and
fluid fighting could have occurred
between individuals or small groups.
Crucially, Carthage's advantage of
reserves would have more easily allowed
them to exploit any vulnerabilities
which developed.
Eventually, the pressures along the
front, and especially the envelopment
around the flanks, would have cracked
Rome's morale.
First, as a trickle, then as a deluge,
riders broke away from the fighting,
fleeing for their lives.
With cavalry, such an affair would have
happened even faster than a route
amongst infantry.
Adrenaline-fueled mounts now made for
the countryside,
perhaps hoping to make safe at the camps
to the rear.
Others, such as Consul Paulus in the
case of Polybius's account, even
attempted to rejoin the infantry.
But, Carthage was in hot pursuit.
As avenues of retreat were cut off, it
is likely that many desperate Romans
made way for the river.
Such a sight must have been incredible
to behold, as hundreds of troops now
spilled into the shallow waters. If our
sources are to be trusted, few made it
across alive.
Certainly, many Carthaginian squadrons
kept up the pursuit to drive the victory
home.
However, their commander, Hasdrubal,
acted with great skill and discretion by
reining in many of his troops for a
charge across to the other side of
battle.
Such restraint is incredibly rare in
ancient battles, especially in the chaos
of a pursuit.
However, our model shows that this
action was likely made far more
practical by the use of reserves who may
well have been kept detached for this
very moment.
Now, such troops could have easily
wheeled into columns for an efficient
transit across the battlefield.
Viewed from the rear of the Roman
infantry, this decisive action might
have been glimpsed as an ominous
billowing of dust clouds moving against
the wind.
Meanwhile, on the eastern flank, the
indecisive fighting between the
Numidians and the Roman allies raged on.
Yet, amidst the indecisive fight, a
turning of the tides may have been
sensed by the observation of dust clouds
from the west.
The final revelation that these were
enemy reinforcements would have been
swift as their columns now fanned out to
envelop the pinned foe.
This pending disaster led to an
immediate collapse of the Roman
position.
Just as had occurred in the west, the
eastern flank now disintegrated.
From above, we can see this destruction
of the cavalry elements.
Once more, Hasdrubal shows great command
by sending off the Numidians in pursuit
while he himself rallies the remainder
of the cavalry to strike at the exposed
rear of the enemy center.
But, this would have taken precious
time.
Meanwhile, as we return to the fight in
the center, we see that the nature of
the fight has evolved.
The first major change is that the
Romans have pushed back, if not
partially broken through, the
Carthaginian center.
The second change is that in the process
of doing so, their formation has lost
all cohesion.
On the ground level, we can see why this
might be the case.
Here, individual soldiers at the front
have shifted around in the process of
fighting or rotating in and out of
combat.
Meanwhile, units further to the rear
have also lost order as they slowly
advance with the front lines or
naturally expands to fill gaps in the
formation.
This has had the effect of turning them
into a wholly unmanageable mob.
But, for now, such a state proves viable
enough to still bully their way through
the Carthaginian ranks, which is only a
few dozen meters deep.
As they do so, we are told by our
sources that the Libyans on the wings
now swing in to strike them from the
flanks.
However, looking at our model, it is
difficult to understand how exactly this
would have worked.
One option would have been to simply
turn to the side and attack the units
next to them.
But, this assumes that there was an
exposed flank to strike at with no
friendly forces in the way.
Another option would have been for the
Libyans to commit to a grander maneuver,
walking nearly a kilometer to reach a
breakthrough in the center or to wrap
around the Roman rear.
Either of these would have taken a
considerable amount of time and control
to execute.
We shall let Dr. Goldsworthy shed light
on the matter.
>> Cannae does seem to be unique in the way
the Libyans function. There are
sometimes troops kept back to be
committed later and of course at Zama
he'll have three lines mirroring the
Roman deployment. But it's not they're
not doing the same sort of maneuvering
that um these Libyans do at Cannae. The
deployment though is fundamentally
unusual because you've had these Libyan
troops, the pick of your troops in
reserve. For most armies reserves aren't
really a big feature of what they do. I
mean the Romans have them, the standard
triplex acies three lines, though again
you could see this more as waves rather
than as true reserves. Only in a few
battles and only later do we hear about
sections of a second or third line being
taken off to do something else like
Cannae for example
where maniples in the rear are taken off
to deal with the collapse of the Roman
left flank. So again it comes back to
that sense that Cannae is a unique
situation. The tactics there are not
part of some long-term plan that uh
Hamilcar and then Hannibal have been
toying with over the decades and trying
to perfect but it's actually something
that Hannibal has come up with for this
situation and facing this particular
Roman army.
>> [music]
>> So it meets the tactical requirements of
this particular problem. Much bigger
Roman army, loads of infantry and maybe
it also has some sense of what the
battlefield is like, what space there is
that I can do this. It's very vague but
it's there are lots of ways it could be
happening and we've probably
oversimplified because again we rush
through the tactic and we want it to
happen really quickly. We also tend to
assume that the battle is a fluid
constant thing without lows in the
fighting, without delays. Even in this
breakthrough that the Romans have come
forward, there are some units still
standing up against them, at least
holding them a little way, and the
Romans hesitate, rest, get their breath
back, come forward again, and attack.
All the attacks later on will tend to
consist more of hand-to-hand combat
because as the battle
continues, those men with missiles have
probably thrown them. So, you might have
light infantry supporting them, but
they'll in the main, you're having to
get the energy, the motivation, the
enthusiasm to charge forward again,
fight hand-to-hand, and hope the enemy
breaks. So, there's a lot more slog and
attrition even with this Roman success.
We probably are wrong to think of it as
happening really quickly and everybody
rushing through, and then the Libyans
somehow, you know,
running a 4-minute mile or so to get up
to [music] in 40 neat formation to hit
the Romans in the flank and trap them.
The whole thing is probably a lot more
gradual than we tend to imagine, and it
may happen unit by unit rather than each
wing of Libyans doing everything at the
same time.
>> But however it happened, it seems that
the commitment of the Libyans helped
further stall the Roman advance, which
had been on the precipice of a
substantial breakthrough.
Perhaps, even at this late juncture, the
legions may yet have had the strength to
press on.
>> [cheering]
>> Yet, this is when Hannibal's cavalry
finally returns to the fight.
Joining them may well have been the
Punic skirmishers who go unmentioned by
our sources.
If it was indeed Hannibal's ultimate
plan to strike a decisive blow to the
rear, it makes sense for at least some
of these units to have wrapped [music]
around the flanks to assist them on this
mission.
But even still, with cavalry and
skirmishers at the rear, there was a
nearly 2-km wide stretch of open ground
for them to somehow cover.
The scales involved are made clear in
our model and force us to contemplate
how this might actually have happened.
Once more, Dr. Goldsworthy will guide us
through this thought exercise.
>> So, you've got your mass of legionaries,
mostly the heavy infantry has started
when compared to triarii in particular
at the back. But, you've also got the
velites. Where have they gone? They've
[music] pulled back, particularly if
they've used their missiles. So, you're
adding in lots of other people into this
mass of a crowd. And again, under normal
circumstances, the heavy infantry could
turn round, form up, charge, and drive
off the light infantry. They probably
won't catch them, but they can keep them
at some sort of distance. But, you can't
do that if there's lots of cavalry there
because then you're going to your
formation is going to break up. You're
going to be vulnerable to the flanks. As
you charge forward, you'll tend to
scatter. It's the sort of thing that
happened at Carrhae um
>> [music]
>> in the 1st century BC, where you can try
and drive the enemy off, but then you
end up as a knot of infantry with the
they're going to be shot by missiles,
hit by missiles that are thrown, charged
in the flank, charged in the rear. So,
that combination of cavalry and light
infantry, which we can guess might be
coming in, closing in on the Roman rear,
is a very formidable one in these
circumstances cuz the Romans are not an
organized battle line anymore. Again,
this is something the model shows well
because you can get a sense of how much
area these cavalry could occupy.
Particularly again, think of them as
groups, troop sizes, squadron sizes, 50,
100, 200 or so. Lots of groups rather
than one or two big blocks, supported by
light infantry that can form up with
some supports, but also with most going
[music] forward as a skirmish line. And
they can move. They're not static. They
can charge in, they can pull back, they
can charge again. So, you're being worn
down and it's sapping the strength. The
probability is though, and clearly the
figures afterwards show that some
Romans, substantial numbers of them, do
break out of this encirclement, which
again comes back to this idea, it's a
very wide area behind the Roman
formation, and the cavalry don't seal it
off completely. Some knots of men will
break out, probably to be amongst the
ones that surrender in the camps
afterwards,
and some of the survivors, you know,
people like Scipio Africanus, they get
out somehow or other.
So, it's never completely sealed, but
it's very difficult and dangerous to get
out in only small numbers, and they will
do so only if they're very determined to
stick together and fight their way out,
not fight their way
uh to sort of stabilize the line.
>> Thus, we now arrive at the end of
tactical maneuvers of the battle.
All troops have been committed, and
their fates sealed by the hours worth of
grappling between the two [music] great
wrestling armies.
The end result is that the Roman army
has been pinned such that any observing
referee would call an end to the match.
But, in war, there is no such arbiter.
So, what can history tell us about the
fate of armies caught in similar
predicaments?
>> Now, armies have got trapped and
surrounded before in other battles on
smaller scales, and they've been
um sometimes shot down from a distance,
you know, I think of the Spartans on
Sphacteria, uh much smaller action, but
nevertheless gives you an idea of how a
a more numerous, more maneuverable group
can take out heavy infantry. There have
been these disasters, there have been
mass slaughters in particularly some of
Alexander's victories over the Persians,
where at Issus, at Gaugamela, even the
think of the um
the Greek mercenary infantry and the
other Persian infantry at the Battle of
the Granicus, where they effectively get
abandoned by their cavalry that's been
driven off, they get surrounded, and
they're wiped out. 2,000 are taken
prisoner, allowed to surrender, and sent
back in chains to slave in the mines,
but the rest are just slaughtered. Now,
Alexander loses a horse
while he's he's leaving. There's still
fighting going on, but it is very
one-sided. The casualties are
overwhelmingly suffered by the beaten
army, by the
the mercenaries and the other Persian
troops, however many there are there.
So, these sorts of things have happened,
but never quite as deliberately as at
Cannae.
>> As Dr. Goldsworthy suggests, there is
indeed a uniqueness [music] to the
nightmare at Cannae which ensued.
We can drop down [music] to the point of
view of a Roman soldier for perspective.
Ancient authors shed some light on the
matter with brutal anecdotes of trapped
soldiers so tightly packed that they
could no longer lift their weapons
[music] to defend themselves, while
others buried their heads in the sands
to hasten their own demise.
On top of this, we must add the
undocumented toll that heat, exhaustion,
>> [music]
>> and deadly crowd surges must have had on
the mob of Romans caught in the
ever-tightening vice grip of the
Carthaginians.
Yet, even with all the attrition they
had endured so far, the legions still
represented a body of troops far more
numerous than the Carthaginians who
surrounded them.
This posed [music] a unique logistical
problem for Hannibal's men on how to
actually dispose
>> [music]
>> of their trapped foe.
>> What you have to remember is that the
50,000 or so Romans and Italians that
die in this phase of the battle have to
be killed
at very short range by muscle-powered
weapons. Some of them could be shot down
by sling bullets. They could be hit by
thrown javelins, other missiles.
But most you're going to have to go
forward and within arms
length, within that distance, kill them
with sword, with spear, with any other
weapons.
The story of Cannae is one of great
tactical subtlety, skill, but also of
extreme brutality. This is a very nasty
encounter. This level of slaughter in
this area
is probably amongst the most vicious and
costly of all ancient battles. Focused
in such an area, the pursuits after
Alexander's victories tend to be spread
out over a little bit longer. There you
still get the nightmarish stories of
some bridging the Assus with corpses,
much as you'll get the stories of the
Aufidius being bridged with corpses.
[music] You know, there's this theme.
There is a sense, yes, a lot of the
sources from Livy, Appian and the like
get a bit carried away, but the
nightmarish element probably is a
reasonable reflection of just what this
was like.
You have to be killed close up, and it
has to be done by muscle power. And
those Romans don't just die, though they
they are again suffering far heavier
losses cuz they're not in organized
fighting fighting line. They're just
masses of desperate, terrified men.
Um some of them fighting to the end,
some of them perhaps giving in,
um but all having to be killed one by
one. This is probably lasting hours to
kill all these people because the
Carthaginians are not machines. They
can't keep fighting. They've got to rest
and then go forward again. And every
time that's going to be harder. Their
swords will be blunted, you know. We
have the the grim statement attributed
to Hannibal that at Zama he thought his
front two lines would would take the
edge off the Roman swords and weapons
before they reached his veterans who
could show them. But that is actually
true. You know, the edges on these
things, all of this is driven by muscle
power. The more they strike into flesh,
into bone, into muscle, the more they
strike armor, the blunted they're going
to get. And the harder it will be to
drive them home. So, it's grim, it's
appalling, it's very gruesome, but
that's the nightmare of Cannae is this
mass mass slaughter.
>> By the time the sun began to set on the
battlefield, [music]
the final tally of destruction was
staggering.
Over 50,000 men [music] lay dead or
dying in an area little more than a few
square kilometers [music] across.
More than half the Roman army had
fallen, including a consul, [music]
two proconsuls, 29 military tribunes, 30
senators, 300 nobles, and many more
souls whom the history books do not
tally.
Even Hannibal suffered losses [music] as
high as 8,000 or roughly 16%.
An exceptionally deadly percentage
[music]
for a victorious army.
To this day, Cannae remains one of the
bloodiest single day's battles in
history.
The fallouts [music] from this event is
best covered in another video. For now,
we will bring our own discussion to
[music] an end.
Looking back on this exercise of
modeling Cannae in [music] true size, we
hope that it has given you a better
understanding of what happened on that
day.
Both from the perspective of how ancient
[music] armies deploy, maneuver, and
fight, but also from the perspective of
the individuals involved whose human
[music] experience should not be
overlooked, and whose understanding is
vital for properly bringing the past to
life.
A huge thanks again to Dr. Goldsworthy
for helping develop this detailed
[music] model of Cannae, and for coming
on as a speaker in this series.
If you enjoy our work, consider [music]
supporting us on Patreon to participate
in polls, catch script previews, and get
HD [music] downloads of all our art.
We owe a huge debt to our current
patrons for funding the channel [music]
and to our researchers, writers, and
artists for making this episode
possible. We certainly couldn't have
done it without this team [music] and
this community. So, be sure to like and
subscribe for more content and check out
these other related [music] episodes.
See you in the next one.
>> Mhm.